<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A table concerning Christ our aduocate and whether remission of sinnes once obtained, can againe be made frustrate, comprised in foure propositions, and fourteene conclusions / by Richard Swaine.</title>
            <author>Swaine, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23511.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143347</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143347</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28401</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28401)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1885:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A table concerning Christ our aduocate and whether remission of sinnes once obtained, can againe be made frustrate, comprised in foure propositions, and fourteene conclusions / by Richard Swaine.</title>
                  <author>Swaine, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Henry Bell, and are to be sold at his shop without Bishops-Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printed in two columns.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Person and offices.</term>
               <term>Atonement.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  London (England) --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:28401:1"/>
            <head>A Table concerning Chriſt our Aduocate, and whether remiſsion of ſinnes once obtained, <hi>can againe be made fruſtrate, compriſed in foure propoſitions, and foureteene Concluſions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRIST is the Aduocate of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <note place="margin">Iohn 17. Rom. 8.</note>onely, and (that) of all which haue been from the beginning of the world, and ſhall be to the end.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Aug. Tract. <hi>41.</hi> in Ioh. Euſeb. Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> 2 Chriſt alſo is the propitiation onely for the ſins of the elect of the whole world: therefore hee is their Aduocate onely. So the Church of Smirna to all the pariſhes, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; Chriſt did ſuffer for the ſaluation of all the world which are to be ſaued; but the elect onely are ſaued. So <hi>Ambroſe, Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>de fide ad gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1. If thou doſt not beleeue, he deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not for thee: therefore he ſuffered onely for the beleeuers.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 22. Galat. 3. Pſalm. 44. Iohn. 12. Rom. 5. 2. Cor. 5. Coloſſ, 1. <hi>Habet ergo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus Dei pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem ſuum. Ambroſ. Ibid.</hi>
               </note> 3 The (world) is ſomtimes taken for the whole world, and all men, as well Elect as Reprobate. Sometime for the more principall part; to wit, the Elect. Sometime for the worſe part of the world, that is, the Reprobate. The author alſo of the booke, <hi>De vocatione Gentium, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. doth declare by examples of many ſcriptures, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a part of the earth, the whole earth; for a part of the world, the whole world; for a part of men, all men to bee nominated: and this as well touching the wicked as the godly. Therefore when he ſaith, that Chriſt is the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for the ſins of the whole world, wee are not inforced by the name of (the whole world) to vnderſtand vniuerſally all men.</p>
            <p n="4">4 There is a difference betweene the worke of our Redemption, and the force (or fruit) of our redemption: for the firſt is once done, the other is eternal, extending it ſelfe as well to them which were from the beginning of the world; euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the work of our redemption was accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, as to them who after the worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> effected, ſhal be to the end of the world. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is properly the efficacie of redemption and propitiation; nothing therefore doth let, but that Chriſt hath beene, and is perpetually the attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſinnes euen of them which were ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the beginning of the world.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſummary of queſtions, whether remiſsion of ſinnes once obtained, can againe be made fruſtrate, compriſed in fourteene Concluſions.</head>
               <p>THe whole courſe of the Goſpell is contained in this ſumme, that it might perſwade vs with beliefe in Chriſt, that our ſaluation is firme &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 5. Math. 7. &amp; 16. Rom. 11.</note>(that is in Chriſt.) If therefore any ſhall ſay, that remiſſion of ſinnes once obtained, by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent falles can be made fruſtrate in the Saints, hee doth ouer-turne the whole ſcope of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. Reade Eſay 38. 44. Mich. 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Only by an abſolute relapſe from piety to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, <note place="margin">Nunquam in nemine ob nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum peccatum ſit irrita remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio. <hi>Zanch.</hi>
                  </note>the remiſſion of ſinnes paſt once obtained, can be done away. But this relapſe the true Saints and elect are not incident vnto: therefore in them forgiueneſſe of ſinnes cannot be fruſtrate.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In the Reprobate true remiſſion of ſinnes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer tooke place: therefore it can neuer in them bee fruſtrate; wherefore in none.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Pro omnibus ſufficienter, pre electis tantum efficaciter. <hi>Zanch.</hi> exſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſticis.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pro omnibus il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis electis. ex Aug.</hi> Iohn. 17. 1, Ioh. 2. Rom. 8</p>
                  </note> 4 For the blood of Chriſt, by which alone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is atchieued, is not according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God, and in deed ſhed out for the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate vnbeleeuers, but only for other many, that is, the Elect, and that for all thoſe many.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Neither did Chriſt pray vpon earth, nor now mediate in heauen, for the reprobate; but onely for the elect beleeuers, &amp; in time to come to beleeue in Him; but remiſſion of ſinnes is obtained by the <note place="margin">Aliqua luce me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes illuminat, nurquam tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pen<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>at illo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is corda, <hi>Zanch. Ioh. 1.</hi>
                  </note>interceſſion of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Likewiſe none but the Elect are truely endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Spirit of Regeneration, who are truely Chriſts, Rom. 8. But without the Spirit of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration forgiueneſſe of ſinnes is not gotten.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">Titus. 1 Rom. 10. 2. Theſſ 3. Act. 13 Rom. 5.</note> 7 So alſo true and iuſtifying Faith is onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Elect: How then can the reprobate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine remiſſion of ſinnes?</p>
               <p n="8">8 To the wicked reprobates there is no peace, as ſaith the Prophet, but of remiſſion of ſinnes doth follow true peace.</p>
               <p n="9">9 From remiſſion of ſinnes doth alwaies follow title to eternall life, and after title the poſſeſſion it ſelf; but the reprobate can neuer haue any title vnto life eternal, and much leſſe to the poſſeſſion thereof.</p>
               <p n="10">10 To attaine remiſſion of ſinnes, and to be iuſtified, are all one Rom. 4. Now none are iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who are not predeſtinated, and elect to iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and life eternall; and whoſoeuer are iuſtified ſhall be glorified Rom. 8. Therefore the Reprobate <note place="margin">Rom. 8</note>ſhall neuer obtaine truely remiſſion of ſinnes, therefore it can neuer be fruſtrate in them, in whom it is not at all.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Gu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>erunt no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ederunt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zanch.</hi> Guſtant ſed <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ox expuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t idem. diſcrimen inter dona ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſancti ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter &amp; dona ſpiritus ſancti regenerantis.</p>
                     <p>Zanchius.</p>
                  </note> 11 By that ſpeech of the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes c.</hi> 6. <hi>It is impoſsible that they who are illuminated, and haue taſted of the heauenly gift, and haue beene made partakers of the holy Spirit, and haue taſted notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the good Word of God, and of the Powers of the world to come, and are fallen away, to be againe renewed to repentance:</hi> it cannot be concluded that the reprobate are endued with the true Spirit of Regeneration, with a true and iuſtifying Faith, and therefore with true remiſſion of ſinnes: yet that many of them are affected with a temporary faith, and ſome taſtes of the holy Spirit, this, and other places, do plainely teach.</p>
               <p n="12">12 The place 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. touching Hypocrites <hi>(For hee that hath not theſe things is blinde, which ſeeth nothing a farre off, forgetting that he was purged from his old ſinnes)</hi> is to bee vnderſtood according to the cuſtome of the holy Scriptures, which do call Saints according to the iudgment of charity, Iuſt, purged from their ſinnes, although they are not all ſo before God, ſo many as are Baptiſed into Chriſt, and confeſſe Him, all ſuch are Sacramentally cleanſed.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Conditionalis propoſitio nihil ponit in forma. <hi>Zanch.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſalm. 1. 112.</p>
                  </note> 13 That of <hi>Ezech. chap.</hi> 18. <hi>(If the Iuſt do auert from his Iuſtice)</hi> is not to be vnderſtood of him who is truely iuſt, but of him who onely ſeemeth of men to be iuſt. For neither can he who is truely righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, finally fall from iuſtice to iniquity, and die therein, of which finall and perfect auerſion the Prophet ſpeaketh: Now hypocrites being iuſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before men, do neuer obtaine true remiſſion of ſinnes before God, therefore it cannot bee proued by this ſentence, that it is fruſtrate.</p>
               <p n="14">14 That <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>So your heauenly Father ſhall do to you, vnleſſe you forgiue euery one to his brother from his heart their offences;</hi> doth not conclude, that ſins once truly releaſed can againe be called into iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but this onely, that ſuch men are deceiued, who thinke their debts to be remitted from God vnto them, when as they do not forgiue treſpaſſes to their brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 12. 33.</note> Euery tongue that ſpeaketh againſt mee <hi>(that is the Holy Ghoſt)</hi> ſhall be condemned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 19.</note> If in this life wee haue onely hope in Chriſt, wee are of all men moſt miſerable.</p>
               <byline>
                  <hi>By</hi> Richard Swaine,</byline>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Henry Bell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop without Biſhops-Gate. <hi>1615.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
